<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 11:46:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 06, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Big tech </b>stocks were dumped by investors as they reacted to <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/02/ai-is-not-the-only-threat-menacing-big-tech" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">the sector’s</a> plans to spend a combined $660bn this year on artificial intelligence. On Thursday the tech-heavy Nasdaq index slid by 1.6%; the S&P 500 fell by 1.2%. Software stocks extended their fall after Anthropic launched an updated version of its Claude<b> </b>model that is designed to carry out financial research.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Novo Nordisk</b> said it would take legal action against <b>Hims & Hers</b>, a telehealth company, for selling a “knock-off” version of its Wegovy <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-world-ahead/2025/11/10/a-second-helping-of-weight-loss-drugs-is-coming" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">weight-loss pill</a>. The Danish drugmaker claims Hims’s pill contains an “untested” compound version of Wegovy’s active ingredient. A partnership between the two companies collapsed last year. Meanwhile <b>Donald Trump</b> launched a government website, <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/09/28/donald-trump-is-waging-war-on-sky-high-drug-prices-can-he-win" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_2">TrumpRx</a>, that will point customers to discounted medicines.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Senior <b>American </b>and<b> Iranian </b>officials will meet in Oman on Friday in a bid to de-escalate rising tensions. America has ramped up its military presence in the Middle East and demanded <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/04/donald-trump-wants-to-end-americas-half-century-conflict-with-iran" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">Iran</a> pause its nuclear programme after the Iranian government violently repressed protests last month. Ahead of the talks Mr Trump told NBC News that Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, Iran’s supreme leader, “should be very worried”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Vladimir Alexeyev</b>, a senior <b>Russian </b>general and deputy head of military intelligence, was shot and injured in Moscow. The assailant is not known. It is the latest such attack on a senior Russian commander since the invasion of Ukraine in 2022. Three officers of Lieutenant General Alexeyev’s rank <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2024/12/17/the-killing-of-a-russian-general-shows-ukraines-spies-remain-lethal" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">have been killed</a> in or near Moscow since December 2024.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>America said it had killed two suspected <b>drug smugglers</b> in a strike on a boat in the eastern Pacific, bringing the death toll of its <a href="https://www.economist.com/interactive/the-americas/2025/11/05/tracking-american-drug-boat-strikes-off-venezuela-coast" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">campaign</a> to at least 128. The Trump administration says it is tackling “narco-terrorists”, though it has provided no conclusive evidence that targeted boats are involved in drug trafficking.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Mr Trump endorsed Takaichi Sanae, <b>Japan’s </b>prime minister, who is hoping to secure a thumping mandate in a snap <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2026/02/05/newborn-parties-are-scrambling-japanese-politics" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_6">election</a> on Sunday. American presidents do not usually publicly weigh in on foreign elections, though Mr Trump has done so before for polls in Argentina and Hungary. He wrote on Truth Social, his social-media platform, that Ms Takaichi “will not let the people of Japan down!”</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Norway’s</b> police launched a corruption investigation into Thorbjorn Jagland, a former prime minister and chair of the Nobel committee, over his alleged links to <b>Jeffrey Epstein</b>. Mr Jagland’s lawyer said they would fully co-operate. The release of documents related to Epstein, a dead sex offender, is <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/05/jeffrey-epsteins-ghost-is-haunting-the-grand-old-men-of-capitalism" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_7">tarnishing the reputations</a> of many from the global elite.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260206-114614</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 11:46:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>