<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 13, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>Bangladesh Nationalist Party</b> won the country’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/05/the-new-bangladesh-is-only-half-built" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">first election</a> since protesters toppled Sheikh Hasina, a despotic prime minister, in 2024. Local media reported that the BNP would have a majority in the 300-seat parliament, with Jamaat-e-Islami, an Islamist group, in second place. The <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2026/02/02/an-election-will-decide-whether-democracy-returns-to-bangladesh" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_1">BNP</a>—led by Tarique Rahman, the scion of a famous political family—has vowed to fight graft and preserve freedom of speech.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Asian stocks</b> fell following a sell-off in <b>American markets</b>. America’s tech-heavy NASDAQ dropped by around 2%, while the S&P 500 slid by more than 1.5%. Gold also fell by more than 3% on Thursday before recouping some losses on Friday. Markets have been <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/08/how-to-hedge-a-bubble-ai-edition" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_2">rattled in recent weeks</a> by fears that artificial intelligence could disrupt a swathe of companies.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Goldman Sachs’s </b>top lawyer resigned over her association with Jeffrey Epstein. Kathryn Ruemmler’s name came up in the more than <a href="https://www.economist.com/interactive/international/2026/02/12/inside-epsteins-network" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">3m pages of documents</a> recently released by America’s Department of Justice relating to the dead sex offender. Epstein had offered to help secure contacts for Ms Ruemmler’s private law practice. He also sent her expensive gifts. She said that by resigning she was putting “Goldman Sachs’s interests first”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Donald Trump announced that he was repealing the Environmental Protection Agency’s<b> “endangerment finding”</b>, a scientific judgment from 2009 stating that greenhouse-gas emissions pose a risk to public health. The ruling had allowed the government to regulate car emissions and require reporting on emissions standards. Mr Trump accused such policies of raising vehicle prices. <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/08/13/trump-2-is-pushing-environmentalists-to-rethink-their-approach" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">Environmentalists</a> are expected to challenge the decision.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The president’s “border czar”, <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/01/24/tom-homan-unleashed" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">Tom Homan</a>, said that federal immigration agents would end their operation in <b>Minnesota</b>. The arrival of nearly 3,000 agents in the state in December sparked widespread protests which intensified after officers killed two American citizens. Mr Homan called the operation a “great success” in arresting “illegal aliens”. American public opinion has turned against <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/01/29/ices-impunity-is-a-formula-for-more-violence" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_5">the president’s deportation campaign</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>America</b> and <b>Taiwan</b> officially signed a <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/10/who-wrangled-the-best-trade-deal-from-donald-trump" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_6">trade agreement</a>, formalising a deal announced in January. America will reduce tariffs on Taiwan to 15%, the same rate that it applies to goods from Japan and South Korea. In return Taiwan will lower levies on America and buy billions-of-dollars-worth of its goods including liquefied natural gas, crude oil and aircraft.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Britain’s</b> top civil servant, Sir Chris Wormald, was forced out by the Labour government after barely a year in the job, making him the shortest-serving cabinet secretary. Sir Keir Starmer, the prime minister, was said to be unhappy with Sir Chris’s sluggish reform of the service. His departure marks the end of a <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/12/britains-predicament-will-get-worse-before-it-gets-better" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_9:gobbet_7">dramatic week</a> for the prime minister, who is barely clinging on to power.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260213-060017</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>