<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 06:01:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 20, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><strong>Donald Trump</strong> warned <strong>Iran</strong> that “bad things will happen” if it fails to reach a deal over its <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2025/09/04/irans-imminent-nuclear-dilemma">nuclear programme</a> within the next 15 days. The president’s ultimatum came after officials confirmed that America has deployed enough military resources in the region to launch an attack on Iran by this weekend. The prospect of war pushed the price of Brent crude, the global oil benchmark, to its highest level in six months.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor</strong>, formerly Prince Andrew, was released from police custody after <a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2026/02/19/what-andrew-mountbatten-windsors-arrest-means-for-the-monarchy">being arrested</a> on suspicion of misconduct in public office. The investigation, which remains open, follows the release of a vast email archive of <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/12/the-epstein-files-tell-a-story-of-justice-denied">Jeffrey Epstein</a>, a dead sex offender whom Mr Mountbatten-Windsor was close to. In a statement King Charles III, his brother, said “the law must take its course.” Mr Mountbatten-Windsor has denied wrongdoing.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Nvidia </strong>is reportedly planning to revise an investment in<strong> OpenAI </strong>to $30bn, instead of the $100bn it originally proposed last year. According to the <i>Financial Times</i>, the deal could be finalised this weekend. The pullback comes amid <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/08/how-to-hedge-a-bubble-ai-edition">investor concerns</a> about the AI sector, which have dragged down shares in tech firms. OpenAI plans to reinvest much of the new capital in Nvidia’s chips.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>America </strong>and <strong>Indonesia </strong>signed a<strong> trade deal,</strong> cutting the Trump administration’s tariffs on Indonesian goods to 19%, down from 32%. Under the agreement, Indonesia will drop duties on almost all American exports. It will also spend $33bn on American products, including oil and aircraft. The agreement was signed at the inaugural meeting of the <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/01/22/trumps-board-of-peace-is-a-distraction-from-the-real-work-in-gaza">Board of Peace</a>, an American-led body set up to rebuild Gaza.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>America’s trade deficit </strong>widened by 33% month on month to $70.3bn in December, fuelled by a surge in imports despite Mr Trump’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/01/has-america-hit-peak-tariff">sweeping tariffs</a>.  The full-year trade deficit was $901.5bn, 0.2% lower than in 2024, largely because of rising services exports. Trade in goods with China fell sharply, but imports from Vietnam, Mexico and India rose.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Venezuela</strong> passed a bill granting amnesty to some political prisoners. The legislation will free hundreds of people locked up during various protests over the past 25 years. Its passage is part of a <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/01/27/how-to-tell-if-venezuela-is-heading-for-democracy">series of reforms</a> following America’s ouster of Nicolás Maduro, Venezuela’s former president. Critics argue that the law does not go far enough and excludes prisoners accused of working with foreign countries.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Mr Trump ordered government agencies to release files related to <strong>aliens</strong> and <strong>unidentified flying objects</strong> because of the “tremendous interest” they have generated. The announcement came shortly after he criticised Barack Obama for revealing “classified information” on a podcast in which the former president claimed that aliens may be real. Mr Trump himself said he did not know whether they exist.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Figure of the day:</strong> 15%, the share of annual GDP spent on the American welfare state. <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/19/did-americas-war-on-poverty-fail">Read the full story</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>
      <i>What do Americans make of Donald Trump’s performance? See his latest poll ratings in our  approval tracker.</i>
    </p>
        <hr>
        <h3>America’s economy is booming</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>The American economy has been on a tear. After a rocky patch last year, when Donald Trump’s tariffs and immigration shutdown weighed on growth<i>, </i>it looks strong again. In the third quarter of 2025, GDP grew by 4.3% on an annualised basis—well above the impressive 2.5-3% clocked up between 2022 and 2024. Fourth-quarter figures, due on Friday, are expected to be only slightly lower, at 2.3%, despite the government shutdown in October and November.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The Trump administration is forecasting even faster growth this year. The One Big Beautiful Bill Act, a tax-cutting law enacted in July, will soon hand Americans $191bn in refunds. Mr Trump is still crusading for interest-rate cuts—which <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/15/donald-trumps-schemes-to-juice-the-economy">might rev up the economy further</a>. The White House’s preferred model, from the Federal Reserve Bank of Atlanta, at one point predicted 5.4% annualised growth for the fourth quarter. That has since been trimmed to 3%—though distortions by tariffs and the shutdown are probably inflating the figure.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Supreme Court decisions incoming</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>America’s Supreme Court may rule on at least one of 27 outstanding cases on Friday. Two particularly notable cases might be ready. The most anticipated is <i>Learning Resources v Trump</i>, a challenge to President Donald Trump’s tariffs from a wine importer and a toy company. When the court heard the case in November, most justices seemed sceptical of Mr Trump’s authority to impose tariffs without clearer congressional approval. If the tariffs are struck down, it could roil global markets—though Mr Trump would have other, more limited <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/11/04/how-donald-trump-can-dodge-a-supreme-court-tariff-block">avenues</a> to reinstate the levies.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The second closely watched case is <i>Louisiana v Callais</i>, which concerns the Voting Rights Act, passed in 1965 to end racial discrimination in elections. The Supreme Court is expected to make it much harder for plaintiffs to challenge electoral maps on those grounds. That would give Republican-led states more freedom to <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2026/02/05/voting-rights-and-wrongs-in-america">draw their own voting districts</a>, which could dilute the voting power of African-Americans and boost the GOP’s chances in future elections.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>America readies itself to attack Iran</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>The largest warship in the world is steaming towards Iran. The <i>USS Gerald R. Ford</i> will soon join another aircraft-carrier already stationed in the Arabian Sea, as America <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/04/donald-trump-wants-to-end-americas-half-century-conflict-with-iran">amasses military might</a> in the Middle East. Dozens of fighter jets and warplanes arrived this week after a second round of nuclear talks between America and Iran proved inconclusive.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>After the meeting in Geneva on Tuesday, Iran’s foreign minister said there had been “general agreement on some guiding principles”. American officials were even less ebullient, and no date was set for a third meeting. President Donald Trump has given the Iranians “15 days” to come back with a more detailed proposal on curtailing their nuclear programme, and has warned that “bad things” will happen if they don’t. The Pentagon says America will be capable of launching a strike by the weekend. <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/05/how-regional-powers-are-thinking-about-a-war-in-iran">An attack</a> is looking likelier by the day.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Coronets to private jets: an oldie remade</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>In “<a href="https://www.economist.com/culture/2026/02/19/as-how-to-make-a-killing-shows-the-inheritance-plot-is-back">How to Make a Killing</a>”, out in America on Friday and elsewhere soon, the outcast scion of a mega-rich Long Island clan schemes to inherit its fortune—by bumping off all his rival heirs. Starring Glen Powell, who is charming even as a serial killer, the delightfully mordant movie is an update of the Ealing comedy of 1949, “Kind Hearts and Coronets”, in which the tale unfolds in Edwardian England.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The new film adopts parts of the original plot, including some elaborate murder methods, and tweaks others. What is striking is how perfectly the story fits today’s tetchily unequal age.<i> </i>Once again, plutocrats set impossible standards of luxury. Meanwhile the “great wealth transfer”, whereby baby-boomers are passing on assets worth trillions of dollars, spreads both jackpots and resentments across the income spectrum. This is one of several recent dramas that depict the ensuing tensions, and is among the most entertaining.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Daily quiz</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>We will serve you a new question each weekday. On Friday your challenge is to give us all five answers and tell us the theme. Email your responses (and your home city and country) by 1700 GMT on Friday to <a href="mailto:QuizEspresso@economist.com">QuizEspresso@economist.com</a>. We’ll pick three winners at random and crown them on Saturday.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Friday: </strong>When Alexander Graham Bell made the first telephone call, who did he call?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Thursday: </strong>Which Canadian business, originally founded in 1670 and noted for its department stores, was finally liquidated in 2025?</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The secret of being a bore is to tell everything.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Voltaire</h3>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260220-060104</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 06:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>