<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 06:31:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 18, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Warner Bros Discovery</b>, a movie-making giant, is restarting talks with <b>Paramount</b> about a potential deal. In December <b>Netflix</b> <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/01/22/the-battle-for-warner-bros-is-only-getting-fiercer" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">announced</a> it would pay $83bn for Warner’s streaming and studio services; Paramount then offered $108bn for the whole company, but its bid was rejected. Paramount has appealed to shareholders directly and reportedly increased its offer, though it has not made the figure public.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Donald Trump said <b>Japan</b> would invest around $36bn in <b>America</b> in the first phase of the two countries’ “massive <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2025/10/30/asia-adapts-to-donald-trumps-transactional-diplomacy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">trade deal</a>”, which was agreed last year. The money will go towards three energy and manufacturing projects, including a natural-gas plant in Ohio. Japan has pledged to invest around $550bn in America in exchange for the Trump administration limiting tariffs on Japanese exports to 15%.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>America</b> and<b> Iran</b> ended negotiations in Geneva with some “guiding principles” for a <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2025/09/04/irans-imminent-nuclear-dilemma" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">nuclear</a> deal, according to Iran’s foreign ministry. Meanwhile an American official said there remained “a lot of details to discuss” and that Iran would present proposals to address “gaps” within two weeks. Earlier Abbas Araghchi, Iran’s foreign minister, spoke with the head of the International Atomic Energy Agency, the UN’s nuclear watchdog.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Nvidia</b>, a <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/10/30/led-by-nvidia-the-ai-industry-has-plans-to-reindustrialise-america" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_4">chipmaker</a>, said it had signed a “multi-year” deal with <b>Meta</b> to supply the tech giant with millions of chips for its AI-related projects. The firms did not disclose the value of the agreement, but it is expected to be worth billions of dollars. Meta plans to spend $135bn on AI this year.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Peru’s</b> Congress removed <b>José Jerí</b>, who served just four months as interim president, for failing to disclose meetings with a Chinese businessman. The South American country has had eight presidents in ten years. Mr Jerí, a former lawmaker, <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2025/10/14/el-boletin-newsletter-political-chaos-in-peru" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_5">had himself replaced an impeached president</a>. Congress will choose his successor on Wednesday. Peru’s next general election is due in April.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>America said it had carried out two strikes on alleged <b>drug-trafficking boats</b> in the eastern Pacific, and a third in the Caribbean, killing 11 people. At least 144 people have been killed since September, when the Trump administration began targeting vessels carrying suspected “narco-terrorists” as part of its <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/10/13/the-new-war-on-drugs" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_6">war on drugs</a>. The White House has <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/12/11/how-much-does-america-know-about-its-boat-strike-targets" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_6">defended the attacks</a>, which some claim violate international law.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Germany’s </b>population is expected to shrink faster than expected—by 5% over the next 25 years—according to the Ifo Institute for Economic Research. The think tank updated its forecast of a 1% decline after the population count in 2025 was revised down from 85m to 83m. The number of people aged between 20 and 66 is expected to decrease by 12%, putting pressure <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2026/01/15/germanys-economy-is-so-bad-even-sausage-factories-are-closing" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_7">on the labour market</a> and pension system.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260218-063109</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 06:31:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>