<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:51:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 17, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>America</b> and<b> Iran</b> ended negotiations in Geneva with some “guiding principles” for a <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2025/09/04/irans-imminent-nuclear-dilemma" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">nuclear</a> deal, according to Iran’s foreign ministry. America has not yet commented. Iran said that American envoys had moved towards “a more realistic” position. Earlier Abbas Araghchi, Iran’s foreign minister, spoke with the head of the International Atomic Energy Agency, the UN’s nuclear watchdog.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Warner Bros Discovery</b>, a movie-making giant, is restarting talks with <b>Paramount</b> about a potential deal. In December <b>Netflix</b> <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/01/22/the-battle-for-warner-bros-is-only-getting-fiercer" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">announced</a> it would pay $83bn for Warner’s streaming and studio services; Paramount then offered $108bn for the whole company, but its bid was rejected. Paramount has appealed to shareholders directly and reportedly increased its offer, though it has not made the figure public.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Tarique Rahman</b> was sworn in as<b> </b>prime minister, after his party won <b>Bangladesh’s</b> <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/05/the-new-bangladesh-is-only-half-built" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">first general election</a> since Sheikh Hasina, a despot, was toppled in 2024. The <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2026/02/02/an-election-will-decide-whether-democracy-returns-to-bangladesh" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">Bangladesh National Party’s</a> return to power, after nearly 20 years, marks a profound shift in Bangladesh’s politics. Mr Rahman has pledged to fight graft—the BNP’s undoing last time—and preserve freedom of speech.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>America said it had carried out two strikes on alleged <b>drug-trafficking boats</b> in the eastern Pacific, and a third in the Caribbean, killing 11 people. At least 144 people have been killed since September, when the Trump administration began targeting vessels carrying suspected “narco-terrorists” as part of its <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/10/13/the-new-war-on-drugs" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">war on drugs</a>. The White House has <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/12/11/how-much-does-america-know-about-its-boat-strike-targets" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_4">defended the attacks</a>, which some claim violate international law.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The<b> European Commission</b> began a probe into <b>Shein</b>, a fast-fashion giant. The EU’s executive arm will look into <a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2025/02/20/shein-attempts-to-mend-its-public-image-before-its-london-debut" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_5">the Chinese firm’s</a> sale of illegal products and investigate whether its online marketplace is designed to be addictive. In November a court in Paris decided that a three-month suspension of Shein’s website was “disproportionate” after an investigation found that it was selling childlike sex-dolls and machetes.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Germany’s </b>population is expected to shrink faster than expected—by 5% over the next 25 years—according to the Ifo Institute for Economic Research. The think tank updated its forecast of a 1% decline after the population count in 2025 was revised down from 85m to 83m. The number of people aged between 20 and 66 is expected to decrease by 12%, putting pressure <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2026/01/15/germanys-economy-is-so-bad-even-sausage-factories-are-closing" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_6">on the labour market</a> and pension system.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Jesse Jackson</b>, a leader of America’s civil-rights movement, died aged 84. Mr Jackson first gained political attention in the 1960s as a protégé of Martin Luther King junior. After <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-world-if/2018/07/05/a-different-dream" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_9:gobbet_7">King’s assasination in 1968</a>, Mr Jackson became a figurehead and twice ran for president. Though unsuccessful, Mr Jackson’s campaigns in the Democratic primaries made him one of the most well-known campaigners for black political rights in America.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260217-185144</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>