<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 22:24:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 03, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>America’s navy</b> shot down an <b>Iranian drone</b> that it said “aggressively approached” the <i>USS Abraham Lincoln</i>, an aircraft-carrier in the Arabian Sea, with “unclear intent”. Last week Donald Trump <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/01/28/is-america-about-to-attack-iran" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">sent an armada</a> to the Middle East, and has repeatedly threatened to <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/01/the-violence-in-iran-could-lead-to-civil-war" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_1">strike Iran</a> if it does not agree to new limits on its nuclear programme and to cut ties with regional proxy groups.</p>
        <p><b>Tech stocks</b> fell after <b>Anthropic</b>, an artificial-intelligence firm, launched an AI tool that can automate some legal work. Shares in legal- and data-services companies plummeted first—that of Thomson Reuters, one such firm, sank by nearly 16%—then <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/01/why-software-stocks-are-getting-pummelled" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_2">software stocks</a> more broadly fell. The tech-heavy NASDAQ index closed down by 1.4%, recovering slightly from a steeper 2.4% drop.</p>
        <p>Mr Trump signed a bill to end the partial government shutdown, after America’s <b>House of Representatives</b> narrowly passed it by 217-214 votes. The measure will fund several agencies until September and the Department of Homeland Security until February 13th, allowing lawmakers to continue negotiating restrictions on <a href="https://www.economist.com/briefing/2026/01/28/immigration-agents-have-become-donald-trumps-personal-posse" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">immigration-enforcement agents</a>.</p>
        <p><b>Disney </b>said that Josh D’Amaro will become its chief executive on March 18th. Mr D’Amaro, who currently runs the company’s theme parks, <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/03/as-bob-iger-departs-disneys-new-boss-faces-a-tricky-balancing-act" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">will replace Bob Iger</a>, who has been in his second stint in the top job since 2022. Investors worry about the century-old studio’s ability to innovate as technology companies reshape the entertainment industry.</p>
        <p><b>Walmart’s</b> market value rose above $1trn for the first time. Investors have been impressed by the <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/05/15/how-walmart-became-a-tech-giant-and-took-over-the-world" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">retail giant’s efforts</a> to develop new technology to take on e-commerce firms such as Amazon. The company recently signed deals with Alphabet and OpenAI to allow users to buy goods from Walmart using their AI products such as Gemini and ChatGPT.</p>
        <p><b>Russia </b>struck <b>Ukraine’s </b>energy infrastructure, ending a pause on such attacks requested by Mr Trump because of freezing temperatures. Ukrainian authorities said the strikes hit power facilities in the capital, Kyiv, as well as several other regions. The bombardment came as American, Russian and Ukrainian officials prepare to <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2026/01/30/peace-negotiations-give-freezing-kyiv-a-hint-of-hope" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_6">meet for talks</a> this week in Abu Dhabi.</p>
        <p><b>Spain’s </b>prime minister, Pedro Sánchez, said his government would seek to ban <b>social media</b> for under-16s. He called social networks a “failed state in which laws are ignored” and pledged to force platforms to introduce “effective age-verification systems”. Governments in Europe and Asia are considering introducing such measures <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/12/10/from-social-media-to-porn-age-checks-are-spreading-across-the-web" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_7">after Australia did so in December</a>.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260203-222430</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 22:24:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>