<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 22:46:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 16, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Iran’s</b> foreign minister, Abbas Araghchi, held talks with the International Atomic Energy Agency, the UN’s nuclear watchdog, about his country’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2025/09/04/irans-imminent-nuclear-dilemma" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">nuclear programme</a> ahead of negotiations with American officials in Geneva on Tuesday. America has deployed a second aircraft-carrier to the Middle East, putting more pressure on Iran, while Binyamin Netanyahu, Israel’s prime minister, called for “all enriched material” to “leave Iran”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Marco Rubio</b>, America’s secretary of state, endorsed Hungary’s prime minister, <b>Viktor Orban</b>, ahead of the country’s parliamentary elections on April 12th. Mr Rubio said President Trump is “deeply committed” to Mr Orban’s success and pledged financial support for the populist-right leader. Mr Orban’s Fidesz party is trailing in the polls behind the Tisza party of <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2026/01/29/peter-magyar-could-defeat-viktor-orban-hungarys-leader" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">Peter Magyar</a><i>, </i>a former ally-turned-critic.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Russia </b>denied it poisoned <b>Alexei Navalny</b> with a toxin found in a South American frog. The opposition leader <a href="https://www.economist.com/by-invitation/2025/09/24/yulia-navalnaya-on-why-europe-needs-a-better-russia-strategy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">died two years ago</a> in a Russian prison. “We do not accept such accusations,” a spokesperson for President Vladimir Putin said. Epibatidine was “highly likely <a href="https://www.economist.com/obituary/2024/02/22/alexei-navalny-didnt-just-defy-putin-he-showed-up-his-depravity" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">the cause</a> of his death”, according to a joint statement by Britain, France, Germany, the Netherlands and Sweden published last weekend.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Ed Miliband</b>, Britain’s energy secretary, and <b>Gavin Newsom</b>, California’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/11/05/gerrymandering-is-now-the-wind-beneath-gavin-newsoms-wings" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">Democratic governor</a>, signed a clean-energy partnership, promising to share technology and attract joint investment. Octopus Energy, a British green-power group, pledged to invest $1bn in Californian renewables, storage and carbon-removal projects. Donald Trump, who has loosened America’s greenhouse-gas regulations, criticised the pact as “inappropriate” and urged Britain not to “get involved” with Mr Newsom.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The <b>Federal Reserve </b>plans to relax capital rules for American banks to encourage more mortgage lending, Michelle Bowman, its vice-chair for supervision, said. The changes would let banks adjust the capital they hold to reflect a loan’s risk, rather than apply a single standard for all mortgages. Officials argue that strict rules have pushed activity to <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2025/05/29/american-finance-always-unique-is-now-uniquely-dangerous" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">non-bank lenders</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Hapag-Lloyd</b>, the world’s fifth-largest container-shipping group, agreed to buy ZIM, an <b>Israeli </b>competitor, for $4.2bn. Carriers ordered record numbers of ships during the pandemic, but freight rates have now slumped and the industry is consolidating. Staff at ZIM went on strike to oppose the merger with the German company and Israeli officials raised national-security concerns. Israel’s competition authority will review the deal.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Robert Duvall</b>, an American actor who played roles in “The Godfather”, “To Kill a Mockingbird” and “Apocalypse Now”, died aged 95. His wife said he passed away “peacefully” at his home in Virginia. Known for meticulous preparation and the variety of characters he portrayed, he won an Academy Award for “Tender Mercies” and received seven Oscar nominations during a career spanning more than six decades.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260216-224605</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 22:46:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>