<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 22:40:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 21, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><strong>Donald Trump </strong>announced he would raise his new global <strong>tariff </strong>to 15% with immediate effect. Mr Trump had initially set a 10% rate under Section 122—which allows the president to impose border levies for up to 150 days—after the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/20/the-supreme-court-strikes-down-donald-trumps-tariffs">struck down the bulk of his other tariffs</a>. Corporate America hopes to recoup an estimated $170bn in duties, a question the justices did not address.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Mr Trump said he was considering limited strikes on <strong>Iran </strong>to pressure it into nuclear negotiations. The president had earlier given Iran a maximum of 15 days to reach a deal; Iran’s foreign minister vowed to send a proposal much sooner. The price of Brent crude, the global oil benchmark, has steadied after reaching its highest level in six months at the prospect of <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/19/the-moment-of-reckoning-between-america-and-iran">imminent war</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Emmanuel Macron</strong>, France’s president, called for calm ahead of a <strong>far-right march</strong> in Lyon. The protest follows the death of Quentin Deranque, a nationalist activist who was kicked and beaten to death by masked men last Saturday. Eleven people, including two parliamentary aides to a hard-left MP, were detained over the incident. Seven are being investigated for murder. The killing has become a <a href="https://www.economist.com/briefing/2025/12/11/once-a-pariah-the-national-rally-is-now-frances-most-popular-party">liability for the left</a> ahead of local elections in March that are expected to shape next year’s presidential race.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Shares in <strong>cyber-security</strong> companies, such as CrowdStrike and Cloudflare, fell after <strong>Anthropic</strong> released a new feature in its Claude artificial-intelligence model. The <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/07/23/the-dark-horse-of-ai-labs">AI firm</a> said the tool “scans codebases for security vulnerabilities” and suggests fixes. The cyber-security slump is part of a broader sell-off in software-related shares, as investors worry about the impact of AI.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Boaz Weinstein</strong>, an activist investor, has offered to buy shares in <strong>Blue Owl’s</strong> business development companies at an expected discount of 20-35%. On Wednesday the private-credit firm spooked markets by permanently restricting exits from a debt fund targeted at retail investors. Mr Weinstein’s offer would allow investors to cash out, albeit while taking a significant loss.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Israeli </strong>strikes killed at least 10 people in eastern <strong>Lebanon</strong>, according to local media. The Israeli army said it had hit sites belonging to Hizbullah, a <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/01/26/hizbullah-irans-most-powerful-proxy-has-been-humbled">Lebanese militia</a>, because they were “a violation of the understanding between Israel and Lebanon”. Earlier Israel struck a Palestinian refugee camp in southern Lebanon, alleging it was a Hamas “command centre”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Britain’s government is considering legislation to remove <strong>Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor</strong> from the line of succession. The former Prince Andrew, who is eighth in line to the throne, was released from police custody on Thursday after being arrested on suspicion of misconduct in public office. He is being investigated over whether he shared classified documents with <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/12/the-epstein-files-tell-a-story-of-justice-denied">Jeffrey Epstein</a>, a dead sex offender. He has denied wrongdoing.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Word of the week: </strong><i>Aso ebi,</i> a term for the matching fabrics guests wear to Nigerian weddings<i>, </i>meaning “cloth of the kin” in Yoruba. <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/19/the-global-triumph-of-nigerian-fashion">Read the full story.</a></p>
        <hr>
        <p>
      <i>What do Americans make of Donald Trump’s performance? See his latest poll ratings in our  approval tracker.</i>
    </p>
        <hr>
        <h3>The blossoming middle-powers bromance</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>On Saturday Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/12/the-rich-world-should-beware-brazilification">Brazil’s</a> president, wraps up a state visit to India and will meet <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2026/01/21/the-remarkable-recovery-of-narendra-modi">Narendra Modi</a>, the country’s prime minister. The pair, who have met many times since Lula was re-elected in 2023, have much in common. Their countries are founding members of the BRICS, an alliance of emerging powers. Both remain chummy with China and Russia. Each has secured sweeping trade deals with the European Union.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Lula’s foreign-policy guru says the trip aims to bolster co-operation in defence, among other things, in part to avoid using “technology of the rich countries”, reported <i>The Hindu</i>, an Indian newspaper. Lula is also seeking to open new markets and forge political ties with other middle powers in the face of a less reliable United States—a record 260 businesses joined his India delegation. Next on his agenda is a visit to South Korea on Sunday, where he plans to convince the country to accept exports of Brazilian beef.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>SCOTUS has struck down Trump’s tariffs. Now what?</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>On Friday the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/20/donald-trump-answers-a-supreme-court-rebuke-with-new-tariff-threats">handed Donald Trump a rare defeat</a>, striking down the bulk of his tariffs. In a 6-3 decision they disagreed with the president’s assertion that a 1970s-era law, the International Emergency Economic Powers Act, allowed him to bypass Congress and set tariffs according to his whims.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>He lashed out at the justices (three of them conservative) who voted against him. They were “very unpatriotic and disloyal to the constitution”, he said, unfoundedly, and “swayed by foreign interests”. And he swiftly laid out plans to circumvent their ruling, imposing a global 10% tariff under a different authority.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>That is only a temporary solution. Mr Trump has options to rebuild the tariffs in full, but they will take time and involve more legal wrangling. And it is unclear what will happen to the money—well over $100bn—importers have already paid in the months since Mr Trump imposed the levies. The immediate economic impact will be greater uncertainty.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Nigeria’s security crisis moves south</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>Over the past week, armed groups have killed dozens of people in a series of attacks in northern Nigeria. The incidents illustrate the country’s interlocking security crises. Islamist militants were responsible for assaults on villages in the north-western Kebbi state. Bandits, motivated by money rather than ideology, were blamed for another set of raids. In response, America has deployed around 100 troops to Nigeria.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The violence follows a brutal attack by jihadists earlier this month, when about 170 residents of the mid-western Kwara state had their throats slit, were shot at close range or burned alive. As Nigeria’s security crisis has worsened, <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/12/a-deadly-attack-shows-nigerias-security-crisis-is-worsening">violence has spread</a> alarmingly close to big cities in the country’s centre.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Both groups could run out of steam as they move south. Jihadists rely on ethnic and kinship networks to recruit; that will be harder farther from traditional strongholds. Bandits will struggle to deepen their influence in the more urban and better governed south. But that will not help anyone they are currently terrorising.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>BDSM hits the silver screen</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>“Pillion”, a skilful debut from the British film-maker Harry Lighton, <a href="https://www.economist.com/culture/2026/02/20/what-to-watch-this-week">releases nationwide</a> in America this weekend. The movie follows Colin (Harry Melling), a quiet and sensitive man who sings in a barbershop quartet and lives with his parents. At the pub one Christmas Eve, he is slipped a note by Ray (Alexander Skarsgard), a taciturn, hunky biker, inviting him to meet the next day. An unpromising hookup in an alleyway marks the start of an intense relationship and a sexual awakening for Colin.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>In BDSM vernacular, Ray is a “dom” and Colin becomes his “sub”. The dynamic extends beyond sex: Colin cooks, cleans and shops for Ray and sleeps on the floor when his work is done. Despite its unusual premise, the film is at heart a story about self-discovery as Colin learns what he will and will not tolerate in a relationship. While Mr Melling’s performance is subtle, Mr Skarsgard’s is utterly compelling.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Weekend profile: Dario Amodei, Silicon Valley’s rebel with a Claude</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>During a recent soirée at the top of Salesforce Tower in San Francisco, Dario Amodei looked faintly out of place. Surrounded by people in business attire, the boss of <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/07/23/the-dark-horse-of-ai-labs">Anthropic</a>, an artificial-intelligence research lab, wore a tatty woollen jumper. While everyone else schmoozed, he acted like he wanted to bolt.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Mr Amodei has a habit of finding himself in awkward situations. In the past week the Pentagon threatened to sever access to Anthropic after he insisted that Claude, the company’s AI model, be used neither for building autonomous weapons nor for mass surveillance. It is the latest clash with <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/11/27/maga-is-divided-over-the-promise-and-perils-of-ai">the Trump administration</a>, which has taken aim at companies seen as insufficiently aligned with its priorities. David Sacks, the president’s AI adviser, has dismissed Anthropic as “woke”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Mr Amodei cuts an unusual figure in Silicon Valley: a founder who appears willing to sacrifice growth for principle. As children he and his sister, Daniela, fantasised about changing the world. After completing a doctorate in biology at Princeton he turned to AI. At <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/12/29/openai-faces-a-make-or-break-year-in-2026">OpenAI</a> he led research on both safety and “scaling laws”—the idea that more computing power makes models more capable. Therein lay a paradox: to create safe AI, he spearheaded the creation of frontier models capable of doing harm. But when he felt OpenAI was prioritising growth over safety, he led a revolt. He, Daniela and five others quit and founded Anthropic in 2021.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The paradoxes did not stop there. Mr Amodei speaks rapturously about AI’s potential to cure disease, yet warns that it could pose grave national-security risks. He worries about the effect on white-collar jobs even as companies deploy Claude for coding and other tasks.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>It sounds contradictory. But to Mr Amodei, safety is not a slogan. He talks with nerdy intensity about exponential gains in computing power, the interpretability of models and the threat of AI-designed bioweapons. He writes long essays—with titles such as “Machines of Loving Grace” and “The Adolescence of Technology”—that veer between optimism and alarm.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Sceptics may note that, despite his jeremiads, Anthropic is worth a fortune. It was recently valued at $380bn, making Mr Amodei a multi-billionaire. But unlike tech bros in Mr Trump’s orbit, he has a disarming lack of swagger. Moreover, refusing to be pushed around by the Trump administration is a brave thing to do. If only more bosses had his backbone.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Mini crossword</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>We publish a new interactive edition of our crossword daily, allowing you to enter and check the answers and see explanations. Try it <a href="https://www.economist.com/interactive/mini-crossword">here</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>There are two sets of clues, one for seasoned cruciverbalists and the other for less experienced solvers. Both give the same answers.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>
      <strong>Cryptic clues</strong>
    </p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>1 across</i> - Sounds a bit eggy for such a heavy burden (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>2 across</i> - Very much in German taxi(4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>3 across </i>- America online went backwards, then north, for a borrowed sum (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>1 down - </i>You, SK looney, chaotically declared martial law (4,3,4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p>
      <strong>Straight clues</strong>
    </p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>1 across</i> - Wooden bar between two animals (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>2 across</i> - American ride-hailing app (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>3 across </i>- Something to pay back (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>1 down - </i>Former South Korean president banged up for life (4,3,4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Email all four answers, along with your home city and country, by 9am GMT on Monday to <a href="mailto:crossword@economist.com">crossword@economist.com</a>. We will pick three winners at random and crown them in Tuesday’s edition.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>The winners of this week’s quiz</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>Thank you to everyone who took part in this week’s quiz. The winners, chosen at random, were:</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Gavin Meacham</strong>, Canberra, Australia</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Kate Marshall</strong>, Toronto, Canada</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Vittorio Ferrario</strong>, Geneva, Switzerland</p>
        <hr>
        <p>They all gave the correct answers of: scarlet (the disease is scarlet fever), hounds, Ginger Baker, Hudson’s Bay company and Thomas Watson (“Mr Watson, come here, I want to see you” Bell said.). The theme is Sherlock Holmes who featured in the stories “A Study in Scarlet” and “The Hound of the Baskervilles”, and lived in Baker Street with a housekeeper Mrs Hudson and friend Dr Watson.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The questions were:</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Monday: </strong>What colour, traditionally worn by a cardinal, is also associated with a childhood disease?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Tuesday: </strong>Grey, blood and basset are words that precede the name of what type of dog?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Wednesday:</strong> Which famous drummer was one of the founder members of the rock group Cream?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Thursday: </strong>Which Canadian business, originally founded in 1670 and noted for its department stores, was finally liquidated in 2025?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Friday: </strong>When Alexander Graham Bell made the first telephone call, who did he call?</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Poetry might be defined as the clear expression of mixed feelings.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>W.H. Auden</h3>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260221-224029</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 22:40:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>