<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 11, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Mark Carney</b>, Canada’s prime minister, said he had a “positive conversation” with <b>Donald Trump</b> after America’s president threatened to block the opening of the Gordie Howe International Bridge linking Ontario and Michigan. Mr Trump accuses Canada of trying to “take advantage” of America. <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/01/25/mark-carney-understands-the-new-world-but-can-he-survive-it" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">Mr Carney</a> pointed out that Canada paid for the construction of the bridge, which used American steel. America also has joint ownership.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>A gunman killed at least nine people at a school and a related residence in the Canadian province of <b>British Columbia</b>, before reportedly turning the weapon on himself. Authorities said that 25 other people were injured during the attack in Tumbler Ridge. A motive has yet to be confirmed.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The president of <b>Samsung Electronics</b>’ chip division, Jaihyuk Song, said the firm had <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2024/08/01/can-samsung-get-its-mojo-back" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_3">got its mojo back</a> thanks to its HBM4 technology. South Korea’s most valuable company is expected to begin production of the new generation of high-bandwidth memory chips this month. It has been struggling to compete with SK Hynix, a local rival.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>During a congressional hearing <b>Howard Lutnick </b>admitted that he visited <b>Jeffrey Epstein’s</b> island with his family in 2012. Documents released by the Department of Justice revealed America’s commerce secretary had closer ties to the dead sex offender than previously thought. Meanwhile an uncovered FBI interview revealed <b>Mr Trump </b>told a police chief in 2006 that “everyone” knew about Epstein’s crimes.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Retail sales in America </b>were unexpectedly flat in December, compared with the previous month. Spending on clothing, furniture and cars fell after an initial flurry of <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/11/27/american-consumers-are-miserable-but-they-keep-spending" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_5">holiday shopping</a>. The disappointing figures, which are not adjusted for inflation, might reflect consumers’ anxiety over rising costs and the impact of Mr Trump’s tariffs. Extreme winter weather might have chilled January sales, too.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Paramount</b>, a film and TV giant, sweetened its offer for <b>Warner Bros Discovery. </b>The firm is trying to derail a <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/01/22/the-battle-for-warner-bros-is-only-getting-fiercer" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_6">competing acquisition</a> attempt by Netflix, which values Warner at $83bn. Paramount agreed to pay the $2.8bn fee that Warner would have to pay Netflix to terminate its bid, plus $1.5bn in fees related to Warner’s debt refinancing.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The Supreme Court of the <b>Philippines </b>ruled that same-sex couples could co-own property. The decision grants property rights under the country’s Family Code law—typically reserved for wedded partners. Same-sex unions are prohibited in the deeply conservative country. The Philippines is also the only country, apart from the Vatican, where divorce is illegal.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260211-060017</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>