<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 12:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 18, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p>Donald Trump said <b>Japan</b> would invest $36bn in <b>America</b> in the first phase of the countries’ “massive <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2025/10/30/asia-adapts-to-donald-trumps-transactional-diplomacy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">trade deal</a>”, which was agreed last year. The money will go to three energy and manufacturing projects, including a natural-gas plant in Ohio. Japan has pledged to invest $550bn in America in exchange for the Trump administration limiting tariffs on Japanese exports to 15%.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Nvidia</b>, a <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/10/30/led-by-nvidia-the-ai-industry-has-plans-to-reindustrialise-america" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">chipmaker</a>, said it had signed a “multi-year” deal with <b>Meta</b> to supply the tech giant with millions of chips for AI-related projects. The firms did not disclose the value of the agreement, but it is expected to be worth billions of dollars. Meta plans to spend $135bn on AI this year.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Ukraine </b>and<b> Russia </b>ended their second day of American-led peace negotiations in Geneva after just two hours. The talks have reportedly been “very tense”. Earlier Volodymyr Zelensky, Ukraine’s president, said that America was putting unfair pressure on him to accept its terms <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2026/02/17/the-war-room-newsletter-is-a-peace-deal-possible" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">to end the war</a>, which include ceding territory to Russia and holding elections.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Sara Duterte</b>, the vice-president of <b>the Philippines</b>, announced that she would run for president in 2028. Ms Duterte is embroiled in a bitter spat with Ferdinand Marcos junior, the current president whom she once supported. Their relationship collapsed after officials launched a corruption inquiry into Ms Duterte in 2024, which resulted in her impeachment. Last year the Supreme Court overturned that decision on procedural grounds.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Britain’s</b> annual <b>inflation</b> rate fell to 3% in January, down from 3.4% in December and the lowest in nearly a year. The drop was driven by a decrease in fuel prices. The <a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2026/02/12/britains-shifting-gdp-numbers" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_5">new data</a> increases the chance that the Bank of England will cut interest rates when it meets next month.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Peru’s</b> Congress removed <b>José Jerí</b>, who served just four months as interim president, for failing to disclose meetings with a Chinese businessman. The South American country has had eight presidents in ten years. Mr Jerí, a former lawmaker, <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2025/10/14/el-boletin-newsletter-political-chaos-in-peru" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_6">had himself replaced an impeached president</a>. Congress will choose his successor on Wednesday. Peru’s next general election is due in April.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>America </b>said it had carried out two strikes on alleged <b>drug-trafficking boats</b> in the eastern Pacific, and a third in the Caribbean, killing 11 people. At least 144 people have been killed since September, when the Trump administration began targeting vessels carrying suspected “narco-terrorists” as part of its <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/10/13/the-new-war-on-drugs" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_7">war on drugs</a>. The White House has <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/12/11/how-much-does-america-know-about-its-boat-strike-targets" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_7">defended the attacks</a>, which some claim violate international law.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260218-120102</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 12:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>