<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 16, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p>Donald Trump said his <b>Board of Peace</b>, a club of world leaders that has been <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/01/22/trumps-board-of-peace-is-a-distraction-from-the-real-work-in-gaza" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">criticised</a> for its $1bn membership fee and Mr Trump’s sole veto power, has pledged more than $5bn towards the reconstruction of <b>Gaza</b>—albeit a fraction of the estimated $70bn required. Ahead of a meeting in Washington, DC on Thursday, Mr Trump claimed that its members would deploy “thousands of personnel” to uphold security in Gaza.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Marco Rubio</b>, America’s secretary of state, endorsed Hungary’s prime minister, <b>Viktor Orban</b>, ahead of the country’s parliamentary elections on April 12th. Mr Rubio said President Trump is “deeply committed” to Mr Orban’s success and pledged financial support for the populist-right leader. Mr Orban’s Fidesz party is trailing in the polls behind the Tisza party of <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2026/01/29/peter-magyar-could-defeat-viktor-orban-hungarys-leader" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">Peter Magyar</a><i>, </i>a former ally-turned-critic.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Russia </b>denied it poisoned <b>Alexei Navalny</b> with a toxin found in a South American frog, on the second anniversary of the opposition <a href="https://www.economist.com/by-invitation/2025/09/24/yulia-navalnaya-on-why-europe-needs-a-better-russia-strategy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">politician’s death</a> in a Russian prison. “We do not accept such accusations,” a spokesperson for President Vladimir Putin said. Epibatidine was “highly likely <a href="https://www.economist.com/obituary/2024/02/22/alexei-navalny-didnt-just-defy-putin-he-showed-up-his-depravity" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">the cause</a> of his death”, according to a joint statement by Britain, France, Germany, the Netherlands and Sweden published last weekend.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Keir Starmer</b>’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2026/02/09/sir-keir-starmer-clings-to-office-but-not-power" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">government</a> scrapped plans to delay local elections in 30 councils across England in the latest blow for <b>Britain</b>’s prime minister. The political U-turn represents a victory for the country’s right-wing populist <a href="https://www.economist.com/briefing/2025/12/11/the-populists-of-reform-uk-already-topping-the-polls-may-climb-higher" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_4">Reform UK</a>, which had launched a legal challenge against the move—initially intended to simplify council mergers. Legal advice warned the government that the delay would likely be ruled illegal in court.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>ByteDance</b>, TikTok’s owner, vowed to curb an AI video-making tool after Disney and other entertainment firms threatened legal action. Social-media platforms have been filled with clips featuring Marvel superheroes and other Disney characters in recent days. <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/03/disneys-new-boss-must-rekindle-its-creative-magic" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_5">Disney’s</a> lawyers accused ByteDance of a “virtual smash-and-grab”. According to the BBC, the Chinese tech giant responded by promising to “strengthen current safeguards”, but did not provide details.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Iran</b>’s foreign minister, Abbas Araghchi, held talks with the International Atomic Energy Agency, the UN’s nuclear watchdog, about his country’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2025/09/04/irans-imminent-nuclear-dilemma" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_6">nuclear programme</a> ahead of negotiations with American officials in Geneva. America has deployed a second aircraft-carrier to the Middle East, putting more pressure on Iran, while Binyamin Netanyahu, Israel’s prime minister, called for “all enriched material” to “leave Iran”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Arco degli Innamorati</b> (Lovers’ Arch), a limestone landmark on the Salento coast in Puglia, Italy, collapsed on Valentine’s Day. It had been battered by strong winds and heavy rains. The arch features in postcards and had been a backdrop for selfies and wedding proposals. The mayor of Melendugno, the municipality where the arch was located, called its loss a “devastating blow”.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260216-200017</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>