<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 09:38:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 04, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>America’s navy</b> shot down an <b>Iranian drone</b> that it said “aggressively approached” the <i>USS Abraham Lincoln</i>, an aircraft-carrier in the Arabian Sea, with “unclear intent”. Last week Donald Trump <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/01/28/is-america-about-to-attack-iran" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">sent an armada</a> to the Middle East, and has repeatedly threatened to <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/01/the-violence-in-iran-could-lead-to-civil-war" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_1">strike Iran</a> if it does not agree to new limits on its nuclear programme and cutting ties with regional proxy groups.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Tech stocks</b> fell in Asia after a similar sell-off in America. It began after <b>Anthropic</b>, an artificial-intelligence firm, launched an AI tool that can automate some legal work. Legal- and data-services companies suffered first: shares in Thomson Reuters, for example, sank by nearly 16%. Then <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/01/why-software-stocks-are-getting-pummelled" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_2">software stocks</a> more broadly fell. The tech-heavy NASDAQ index closed down by 1.4%.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Mr Trump signed a bill to end the partial government shutdown, after it narrowly passed the <b>House of Representatives</b> by 217-214 votes. The measure will fund several agencies until September and the Department of Homeland Security until February 13th, allowing lawmakers to continue negotiating restrictions on <a href="https://www.economist.com/briefing/2026/01/28/immigration-agents-have-become-donald-trumps-personal-posse" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">immigration-enforcement agents</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Seif al-Islam Qaddafi</b>, the son of <b>Libya’s</b> former dictator Muammar, was reportedly killed. The circumstances are unclear, but his lawyer said he was assassinated at home by “unknown assailants”. Mr Qaddafi <i>fils</i> was once seen as the most influential person in <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2021/10/02/could-libya-be-ruled-again-by-a-qaddafi" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">Libya</a> after his father, and his heir apparent, before the regime collapsed. He ran for president in 2021 but the elections were derailed.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Disney</b> named Josh D’Amaro as its new chief executive, starting in March. Mr D’Amaro currently runs the company’s theme parks. He will replace Bob Iger, who has been in his second stint in the top job since 2022. Theme parks are now the firm’s most profitable division, but the creative engine on which they rely <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/03/as-bob-iger-departs-disneys-new-boss-faces-a-tricky-balancing-act" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">seems to be sputtering</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Walmart’s</b> market value rose above $1trn for the first time. Investors have been impressed by the <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/05/15/how-walmart-became-a-tech-giant-and-took-over-the-world" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_6">retail giant’s efforts</a> to develop new technology to take on e-commerce firms such as Amazon. Walmart recently signed deals with Alphabet and OpenAI that allow its customers to use AI to buy goods.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Spain’s </b>prime minister, Pedro Sánchez, said his government would seek to ban <b>social media</b> for under-16s. He called social networks a “failed state in which laws are ignored”, pledging to force platforms to introduce effective age-verification systems. Governments across Europe and Asia are considering introducing such measures. <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/12/10/from-social-media-to-porn-age-checks-are-spreading-across-the-web" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_7">Australia did so in December</a>. Elon Musk, X’s owner, called Mr Sánchez a “fascist totalitarian”.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260204-093850</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 09:38:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>