<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 10, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Paramount</b>, a film and TV giant, sweetened its offer for <b>Warner Bros Discovery</b> as part of attempts to derail a <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/01/22/the-battle-for-warner-bros-is-only-getting-fiercer" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">competing acquisition</a> of Warner by Netflix, which values the former at $83bn. Paramount agreed to pay Warner’s $2.8bn fee to terminate its rival bid from Netflix, along with $1.5bn in fees related to Warner’s debt refinancing. Warner shareholders are set to vote on the offer from Netflix by April.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Mark Carney</b>, Canada’s prime minister, said he had a “positive conversation” with <b>Donald Trump</b> after America’s president threatened to block the opening of a bridge linking the two countries over claims that Canada was trying to “take advantage”. <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/01/25/mark-carney-understands-the-new-world-but-can-he-survive-it" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">Mr Carney</a> said Canada had paid for the construction of the Gordie Howe International Bridge and that American steel was used. America also has an ownership stake.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>McKinsey</b>, a <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/08/03/how-mckinsey-lost-its-edge" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">consulting giant</a>, agreed to sell its investment arm, MIO Partners, to Neuberger Berman, a fund manager. The deal follows scandals related to conflicts of interest between <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2025/08/07/mckinsey-and-its-peers-need-a-new-strategy-and-some-humility" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">McKinsey’s consultants</a> and its investment office. In 2021 America’s Securities and Exchange Commission fined MIO $18m, citing “compliance failures”. MIO manages around $20bn in assets for current and former McKinsey employees.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Shares in <b>Kering</b>, a Paris-listed luxury group, rose by 14% on signs that a restructuring launched by its new chief executive, <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/06/19/can-a-car-boss-turn-around-guccis-owner" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">Luca de Meo</a>, is bearing fruit. Revenues in the fourth quarter fell by just 3%, better than analysts had expected. Sales at Gucci, its flagship brand, improved. Over the last three years the group’s shares had plunged by more than half.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Air Canada cancelled all <b>flights</b> to <b>Cuba</b> after the Caribbean country said it would not be able to supply international airlines with aviation fuel. The Trump administration has enforced an oil blockade on the island, claiming its government is a <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/01/05/cubas-regime-is-now-in-donald-trumps-sights" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">threat to America</a>. On Monday Claudia Sheinbaum, Mexico’s president, accused America of trying to “strangle” Cuba and vowed to help the island through “diplomatic actions”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Botswana</b>, a leading diamond producer, unveiled tax hikes to offset a sales slump and a budget deficit caused by the increasing popularity of cheaper <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/02/06/dont-propose-with-a-diamond" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_6">lab-grown diamonds</a>. The country’s finance ministry wants to increase corporate taxes by 2.5 percentage points to 24.5%. A similar increase is also planned for Botswana’s top rate of personal income tax, bringing it to 27.5%.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The Supreme Court of the <b>Philippines </b>ruled that same-sex couples could co-own property. The decision grants property rights under the country’s Family Code law—typically reserved for wedded partners. Same-sex unions are prohibited in the deeply conservative country. The Philippines is also the only country, apart from the Vatican, where divorce is illegal.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260210-200017</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>