<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 20:01:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 12, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Donald Trump’s</b> “border czar”, <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/01/24/tom-homan-unleashed" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">Tom Homan</a>, said that federal immigration agents would end their operation in <b>Minnesota </b>after more than two months. The arrival of nearly 3,000 agents in the state sparked widespread protests which intensified after officers killed two American citizens. Mr Homan said the operation had been a “great success” in arresting “illegal aliens”. American public opinion has turned against <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/01/29/ices-impunity-is-a-formula-for-more-violence" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_1">Mr Trump’s deportation campaign</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>CK Hutchison</b>, a Hong Kong-based conglomerate, threatened legal action against Maersk should the Danish firm take control of two ports at either end of the <b>Panama Canal</b>. Last month Panama’s Supreme Court cancelled CK Hutchison’s contract to run the facilities; the government said a Maersk affiliate would temporarily take over. The court’s decision <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/02/05/the-panama-canal-is-a-hinge-point-in-donald-trumps-new-order" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_2">was a boon to Mr Trump</a>, who wants to limit China’s sway over the canal.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Britain’s</b> top civil servant, Sir Chris Wormald, was forced out by the Labour government after barely a year in the job. He is the shortest-serving cabinet secretary since the post was created in 1916. Mr Wormald’s departure will further destabilise <b>Sir Keir Starmer’s</b> government. This week Sir Keir <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/12/britains-predicament-will-get-worse-before-it-gets-better" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">barely clung on</a> to power after Labour colleagues threatened to turn against him.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>WhatsApp </b>said that Russia tried to “fully block” its services as part of a crackdown on foreign technology. The government banned other platforms owned by Meta, including Facebook and Instagram, in 2022; WhatsApp has continued to be Russia’s most popular messaging app with more than 100m users. The Kremlin wants Russians to switch to <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2025/09/04/vladimir-putin-is-building-a-super-app" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">MAX</a>, its own app with dodgy security.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Sanofi </b>ousted its boss of six years, Paul Hudson. The French pharma giant has not developed as many successful new drugs as it had hoped to during his tenure. Several disappointed in late-stage trials. Mr Hudson will be replaced by Belén Garijo, who currently leads Merck, a German rival, and previously spent 15 years at the French firm. Shares in Sanofi fell by 5% on the news.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Nuveen</b>, an American asset manager, agreed to buy <b>Schroders</b>, one of Britain’s oldest and most venerable fund managers, for $13.5bn. The combined firm will have $2.5trn of assets under management. The share price of Schroders has plunged in recent years as the company struggled to cut costs. Schroders said its 221-year-old brand would be retained.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Ukraine’s </b>president, Volodymyr Zelensky, criticised the International Olympic Committee after it disqualified a Ukrainian skeleton rider at its <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2025/12/18/italy-is-using-the-winter-olympics-to-appeal-to-the-ultra-wealthy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_7">2026 Winter Games</a>. Officials decided that Vladyslav Heraskevych’s wearing of a helmet that depicted athletes killed during Russia’s invasion broke competition rules. Mr Zelensky said the IOC should “not play into the hands of aggressors”.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260212-200159</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 20:01:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>