<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 13, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Sultan Ahmed bin Sulayem</b> (pictured) left his roles as chair and chief executive of <b>DP World</b>, an Emirati logistics giant, after his association with Jeffrey Epstein, a dead sex offender, <a href="https://www.economist.com/interactive/international/2026/02/12/inside-epsteins-network" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">emerged in documents</a> released by America’s Justice Department. Dubai’s government said he would be succeeded by Essa Kazim as chair and Yuvraj Narayan as chief executive. Earlier <b>Goldman Sachs’s </b>top lawyer, Kathryn Ruemmler, resigned over her links to Epstein.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>America’s annual <b>inflation</b> rate fell further than expected in January, to 2.4%. That was down from 2.7% in December and below economists’ expectations of 2.5%. The core rate, which strips out volatile food and energy prices, was in line with expectations at 2.5%. The figures reassured investors that the Federal Reserve will continue to cut interest rates this year.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The <b>Trump administration</b> sued <b>Harvard University</b>, accusing it of withholding admissions data. The Justice Department said it was investigating whether Harvard has racially discriminated in its admissions process since 2023, when the Supreme Court banned <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2024/09/19/what-is-the-effect-of-the-supreme-courts-affirmative-action-ban" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_3">affirmative action</a>, policies that prioritise certain racial groups. Donald Trump has previously <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/08/31/donald-trump-comes-for-americas-public-universities" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">withheld federal funds from campuses</a>, including Harvard’s, for not complying with his reforms to university policies.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Germany’s </b>chancellor, Friedrich Merz, said that the post-war world order “no longer exists” as he opened the Munich Security Conference. Before departing to the forum, Marco Rubio, America’s secretary of state, admitted relations with Europe were “at a defining moment”. He is expected to adopt a softer approach than J.D. Vance, the vice-president, who last year rebuked European allies over free speech.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Anthropic </b>raised $30bn in its latest funding round, bringing the AI company’s valuation to $380bn. Investors in the round included GIC, Singapore’s sovereign wealth fund, and Coatue, an American fund. Anthropic said it would continue to focus on developing AI products for business, an area where it has gained an edge over its rivals. The firm could <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/12/16/spacex-openai-anthropic-and-their-giga-ipo-dreams" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_5">launch an initial public offering</a> this year.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Russia’s </b>central bank cut interest rates by half a percentage point, to 15.5%. Most economists had expected it to hold rates steady to rein in inflation. The annual inflation rate was 5.6% in December, down from November, but above the bank’s 4% target. Still, the bank wants to buoy growth as the economy flags because of Western sanctions and high borrowing costs.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Britain’s </b>High Court ruled that the government’s banning of <b>Palestine Action</b> was unlawful. Ministers had <a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2025/11/20/britain-struggles-to-distinguish-between-protest-and-terrorism" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_7">labelled the pro-Palestinian protest group</a> a terrorist organisation, arguing that its activities, which included breaking into a military air base, were a security threat. Just showing support for the group was made punishable by prison, outraging free-speech advocates. The ruling is another blow to <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/12/britains-predicament-will-get-worse-before-it-gets-better" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_7">Sir Keir Starmer’s struggling government</a>.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260213-200016</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:00:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>