<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 12, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>America’s</b> House of Representatives voted in favour of ending the national emergency that Donald Trump invoked to impose <b>tariffs</b> on <b>Canadian</b> imports last year. The measure now goes to the Senate, though the president will probably veto it if it reaches his desk. Still, the House vote is a symbolic rebuke of Mr Trump’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/10/who-wrangled-the-best-trade-deal-from-donald-trump" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">trade policies</a>, with six Republicans joining Democrats to support the resolution.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Police identified Jesse Van Rootselaar, an 18-year-old transgender woman, as the suspected shooter in an attack on a school and nearby residence in the Canadian province of <b>British Columbia</b>. Nine people were killed in the shooting, including the attacker, who turned the gun on herself. Earlier authorities said that at least 25 other people were injured. A motive has yet to be confirmed.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>America’s economy</b> added 130,000 jobs in January, almost double the number that analysts had been expecting, indicating that <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/11/30/why-worries-about-american-job-losses-are-overstated" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_3">the labour market</a> might have picked up after a difficult few months. The unemployment rate also fell to 4.3%, a slight dip from the previous month. The figures may discourage the Federal Reserve from lowering interest rates as fast as Mr Trump would like.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Italy’s</b> government passed a bill authorising the use of naval blockades to stop migrants entering the country. The measure—championed by <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2025/10/16/giorgia-meloni-marks-her-third-anniversary-in-great-political-shape" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_4">Giorgia Meloni</a>, Italy’s populist prime minister—would be rolled out when there is a surge of migrants attempting to reach the country’s shores. Earlier this week European Union lawmakers approved new measures to counter illegal immigration, including swifter repatriation.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Following a meeting with <b>Binyamin Netanyahu</b> in Washington, <b>Mr Trump</b> said “nothing definitive” was decided about dealing with Iran’s nuclear programme, but that negotiations with the Islamic Republic would continue. Earlier, during a speech to mark the 47th anniversary of the Islamic revolution, Iran’s president said he was prepared to allow <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/04/donald-trump-wants-to-end-americas-half-century-conflict-with-iran" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_5">nuclear</a> inspections, and reiterated that the country was not building an atomic weapon.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Pershing Square, a hedge fund run by <b>Bill Ackman</b>, an activist investor, disclosed a stake in <b>Meta</b> worth around 10% of the fund’s capital. Mr Ackman said investors’ fears about Meta’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/02/05/the-data-centre-investment-spree-shows-no-signs-of-stopping" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_6">heavy spending on AI</a> had undervalued the company, and that it stands to benefit from the technology. Earlier Meta announced that it had begun construction on a $10bn data centre in Indiana.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Kraft Heinz</b> paused plans to split into two companies. <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/07/17/kraft-heinz-is-not-the-only-food-giant-in-trouble" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_7">The struggling American food giant</a> originally announced in September that it would break up its slow-growing store brands from its seasonings and sauces business. Steve Cahillane, Kraft Heinz’s new boss, said the company’s problems were “fixable” and would instead invest $600m to beef up its marketing efforts and product offerings.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260212-060017</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>