<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 09, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Anas Sarwar</b>, the Scottish Labour leader, urged <b>Sir Keir Starmer</b> to resign. He is the most senior politician in the prime minister’s party to call for him to quit. Sir Keir’s communications chief and his top adviser have both stepped down over their boss’s decision to appoint <a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2026/02/04/britains-worst-political-scandal-of-this-century" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">Peter Mandelson</a> as ambassador to America despite Lord Mandelson’s ties to Jeffrey Epstein, a dead sex offender.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>American forces captured a tanker that was shipping <b>Venezuelan oil</b> in the Indian Ocean. America’s Department of War accused the vessel of breaching the country’s “quarantine” of crude exports from <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/01/27/how-to-tell-if-venezuela-is-heading-for-democracy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">Venezuela</a>. America has relaxed its blockade since toppling Nicolás Maduro, the country’s dictator, but continues to block much of its oil exports. It is the eighth tanker America has seized for carrying Venezuelan oil.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Bangladesh </b>struck a trade deal with <b>America</b> setting a tariff of 19% on most exports. The initial proposed levy, of 37%, was lowered to 20% last year. In addition some clothing made with American cotton or fibres will enter America’s market duty-free. <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2026/02/02/an-election-will-decide-whether-democracy-returns-to-bangladesh" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">Muhammad Yunus</a>, Bangladesh’s interim leader, said the agreement would bolster the garment sector, which accounts for the bulk of the country’s exports.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Novo Nordisk</b>, a Danish maker of weight-loss drugs, filed a lawsuit against <b>Hims & Hers</b>, an American e-pharmacy. <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/12/15/the-plan-to-rescue-novo-nordisk" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_4">Novo</a> accuses Hims of infringing its patents on semaglutide, an ingredient in its Ozempic and Wegovy products, and wants Hims’s copycat versions of the drugs to be banned. Novo’s share price rose by more than 7% on the news. Hims’s fell by around 25%.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Alphabet</b>, Google’s parent company, will reportedly raise $20bn from a bond sale on Monday, as it seeks to finance its investments in AI. Last week Alphabet said it anticipated up to $185bn in capital expenditure this year, including on <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/09/30/the-murky-economics-of-the-data-centre-investment-boom" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_5">data centres</a>. In a rare move for a technology company, Alphabet is also apparently courting banks to buy a 100-year bond.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Eritrea</b> responded to <b>Ethiopia</b> after it said that Eritrea was occupying parts of Ethiopia and supporting armed groups in the country, calling the accusations “patently false and fabricated”. Ethiopia has been fighting rebels in the Tigray region, which borders Eritrea. Tensions have risen in recent years between the two neighbours; <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2025/11/13/ethiopia-is-perilously-close-to-another-war" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_6">Ethiopia</a> wants to acquire at least one of Eritrea’s Red Sea ports.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>King Charles III </b>said he felt “profound concern” over allegations that his brother, Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, misled officials about his ties to <b>Epstein</b>, after police began assessing a complaint over the alleged sharing of confidential material with Epstein. Meanwhile Ghislaine Maxwell, <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/05/jeffrey-epsteins-ghost-is-haunting-the-grand-old-men-of-capitalism" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_7">Epstein’s</a> accomplice serving a 20-year sentence, refused to answer questions from America’s House Oversight Committee, invoking her Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260209-200018</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>