<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 20:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 06, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p>America’s<b> stock market</b> rebounded on Friday after a run of sell-offs. The Dow Jones Industrial Average hit a new high, surpassing 50,000. The S&P 500 and NASDAQ indexes both climbed by more than 1.5%. Investors have been spooked this week by big tech’s vast artificial-intelligence spending plans and a model released by Anthropic, an AI firm, that could challenge some <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/01/why-software-stocks-are-getting-pummelled" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">software companies</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>At least 31 people were killed in a <b>suicide-bomb attack</b> on a Shia mosque in Islamabad, <b>Pakistan’s </b>capital. Officials said nearly 170 people were injured. The minority Shia Muslim sect in Pakistan has been the target of violence in the past. <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-economist-explains/2024/02/02/why-is-there-so-much-violence-in-balochistan" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">Militant violence</a> has risen there recently; a suicide bombing in Islamabad in November—the first attack on civilians there in a decade—killed twelve people.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The <b>EU </b>proposed a ban on all services provided to <b>Russian </b>oil tankers, to force the Kremlin back to negotiations to end the war in Ukraine. If backed by all EU member states and G7 countries, the sanctions would <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/01/27/the-west-and-ukraine-are-capsizing-russias-shadow-fleet" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">squeeze Russia’s energy sector</a> further by cutting off access to ports and insurance services, for example.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Stellantis </b>booked a €22.2bn ($26.5bn) charge in its second-half earnings for 2025 to reflect an unwinding of investments in its electric-vehicle business due to lacklustre demand. The European carmaker (whose largest shareholder part-owns <i>The Economist’s </i>parent company) has forecast a net loss of up to €21bn for the period as a result. Its shares fell by more than 20% today.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>American </b>and<b> Iranian </b>officials met for talks in Oman amid rising tensions. Abbas Araghchi, Iran’s foreign minister, said the talks were “positive” but neither side offered further details. America has sent warships to the Middle East and demanded <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/04/donald-trump-wants-to-end-americas-half-century-conflict-with-iran" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_5">Iran</a> pause its nuclear programme after the Iranian government violently repressed protests last month.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Sergei Lavrov,<b> Russia’s </b>foreign minister,<b> </b>blamed Ukraine for the shooting of <b>Vladimir Alexeyev</b>, a senior Russian general. Mr Lavrov did not provide any evidence. Lieutenant General Alexeyev was hospitalised after the shooting in Moscow. It was the latest of several attacks on high-ranking Russian officers. Three lieutenant generals <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2024/12/17/the-killing-of-a-russian-general-shows-ukraines-spies-remain-lethal" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_6">have been killed</a> in or near the capital since December 2024.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Police confiscated more than 25 tonnes of <b>cannabis </b>in a raid in Skopje, <b>North Macedonia’s </b>capital, the biggest-ever seizure in the country. Officers targeted two operations that were suspected of pretending to cultivate the drug for medicinal purposes, which is legal. Last month police in neighbouring Serbia weeded out a group that was smuggling cannabis thought to have originated in North Macedonia.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260206-200018</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 20:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>