<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 06:48:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 17, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p>Oil prices rose ahead of negotiations between <b>Iran</b> and <b>America</b> in Geneva on Tuesday. Donald Trump said he would be “indirectly” involved in the talks about Iran’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2025/09/04/irans-imminent-nuclear-dilemma" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">nuclear programme</a>. Earlier America deployed a second aircraft-carrier to the Middle East, raising tensions. On Monday Iran’s foreign minister, Abbas Araghchi, held talks with the International Atomic Energy Agency, the UN’s nuclear watchdog.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>BHP</b>, the world’s biggest mining company by market capitalisation, reported stronger-than-expected half-year results, driven by soaring demand for <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/10/23/trumponomics-is-warping-the-worlds-copper-markets" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">copper</a>. The Australian group said revenue rose by 11% year on year to $27.9bn in the six months to the end of December. Net profit rose by nearly 30%. Shares in the company opened 7.5% higher.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Lawmakers in New Mexico passed legislation to launch an investigation into Zorro Ranch, a mansion owned by<b> Jeffrey Epstein</b>. The dead sex offender allegedly trafficked and abused girls and women there. A bipartisan committee will investigate which <a href="https://www.economist.com/interactive/international/2026/02/12/inside-epsteins-network" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_3">ranch guests and state officials</a> may have known. Meanwhile Thomas Pritzker, a hotel magnate, stepped down as Hyatt’s executive chair after documents revealed his ties to Epstein.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Ed Miliband</b>, Britain’s energy secretary, and <b>Gavin Newsom</b>, California’s <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2025/11/05/gerrymandering-is-now-the-wind-beneath-gavin-newsoms-wings" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_4">Democratic governor</a>, signed a clean-energy partnership, promising to share technology and attract joint investment. Octopus Energy, a British green-power group, pledged to invest $1bn in Californian renewables, storage and carbon-removal projects. Mr Trump, who has loosened America’s greenhouse-gas regulations, criticised the pact as “inappropriate” and urged Britain not to “get involved” with Mr Newsom.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The <b>Federal Reserve </b>plans to relax capital rules for American banks to encourage more mortgage lending, Michelle Bowman, its vice-chair for supervision, said. The changes would let banks adjust the capital they hold to reflect a loan’s risk, rather than apply a single standard for all mortgages. Officials argue that strict rules have pushed activity to <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2025/05/29/american-finance-always-unique-is-now-uniquely-dangerous" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_5">non-bank lenders</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Hapag-Lloyd</b>, the world’s fifth-largest container-shipping group, agreed to buy ZIM, an <b>Israeli </b>competitor, for $4.2bn. Carriers ordered record numbers of ships during the pandemic, but freight rates have now slumped and the industry is consolidating. Staff at ZIM went on strike to oppose the merger with the German company and Israeli officials raised national-security concerns. Israel’s competition authority will review the deal.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Robert Duvall</b>, an American actor who played roles in “The Godfather”, “To Kill a Mockingbird” and “Apocalypse Now”, died aged 95. His wife said he passed away “peacefully” at his home in Virginia. Known for meticulous preparation and the variety of characters he portrayed, he won an Academy Award for “Tender Mercies” and received seven Oscar nominations during a career spanning more than six decades.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260217-064841</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 06:48:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>