<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 16, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Kaja Kallas</b>, the vice-president of the European Commission, criticised <b>America’s</b> “fashionable euro-bashing” and said other countries “look up to us”. Ms Kallas’s remarks came at the end of a tense Munich Security Conference. A day earlier Marco Rubio, America’s secretary of state, won over the audience by playing up ties between the allies—though he also delivered a <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2026/02/14/america-offers-europe-warmer-words-but-a-deep-chill-remains" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">blunt message</a> that national interests are taking over the “so-called global order”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Israeli</b> air strikes killed at least<i> </i>12 people in Gaza on Sunday, according to Palestinian officials. Israel said the attacks were retaliation for Hamas having violated a ceasefire agreement a day earlier. Meanwhile, Israel approved a plan to designate areas of the occupied <b>West Bank</b> as “state property”, a move that has been criticised as de facto annexation.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>OpenAI</b> hired Peter Steinberger, the founder of <b>OpenClaw</b>, an open-source project that lets users build personal AI agents. Sam Altman, OpenAI’s founder, said he plans to launch a similar service as one of his firm’s “core product offerings”. OpenClaw drew attention last month when thousands of its agents began <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/02/a-social-network-for-ai-agents-is-full-of-introspection-and-threats" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_3">posting on Moltbook</a>, an online chat forum.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Herman Halushchenko, a former <b>Ukrainian</b> minister, was arrested while trying to leave the country. Mr Halushchenko was one of several senior officials to resign last year after being implicated in an alleged $100m <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2025/11/17/a-huge-corruption-scandal-threatens-ukraines-government" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_4">embezzlement scheme</a>. Separately, Volodymyr Zelensky, the president, said on Saturday that Ukraine needed “two months of ceasefire” to hold an election, which America has been pushing for as a condition of continued security guarantees.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>American forces interdicted and boarded a ship in the<b> Indian ocean</b>, according to the Pentagon. The <i>Veronica III</i>, a vessel under sanctions, left the coast of <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/01/27/how-to-tell-if-venezuela-is-heading-for-democracy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_5">Venezuela</a> with a hold full of oil on January 3rd, the day that America’s armed forces captured Nicolás Maduro, the country’s dictator. It is the second <b>oil tanker</b> carrying Venezuelan oil that America has seized this month.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>North Korea</b> unveiled a new housing district in Pyongyang, the capital, for families of soldiers killed fighting alongside Russian forces in Ukraine. State media showed Kim Jong Un touring “Saeppyol Street” with his daughter, <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2026/01/08/the-teenage-girl-who-may-rule-north-korea" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_6">Kim Ju Ae</a>, who is increasingly believed to be his heir. According to South Korean intelligence, the hermit kingdom has sent thousands of troops to aid Russia’s war.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>ByteDance</b> vowed to curb an AI video-making tool after Disney and other entertainment firms threatened legal action. Social-media platforms have been filled with clips featuring Marvel superheroes and other Disney characters in recent days. <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/03/disneys-new-boss-must-rekindle-its-creative-magic" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_7">Disney’s</a> lawyers accused ByteDance of a “virtual smash-and-grab”. According to the BBC, the Chinese tech giant responded by promising to “strengthen current safeguards”, but did not provide more details.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260216-060017</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>