<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 06:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 09, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2025/10/09/meet-japans-fireball-takaichi-sanae-its-polarising-new-leader" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">Takaichi Sanae</a> won a <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2026/02/08/how-japans-prime-minister-will-use-her-massive-new-mandate" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_1">landslide</a> in <b>Japan’s snap election</b>. The leader of the Liberal Democratic Party, who became prime minister a few months ago, secured a two-thirds “supermajority” in the lower house. The main centre-left opposition, the Central Reform Alliance, lost half its seats. Armed with a fresh mandate, Ms Takaichi is expected implement a looser fiscal policy. Japanese stocks surged on the news.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Jimmy Lai</b>, one of Hong Kong’s most famous <a href="https://www.economist.com/china/2025/12/14/jimmy-lais-judgment-day" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_2">pro-democracy advocates</a>, was sentenced to a total of 20 years in prison for collusion with foreign forces and sedition, crimes under the territory’s national-security law. He was convicted in December. The 78-year-old media mogul has already spent more than 1,800 days behind bars for unauthorised assembly and fraud.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Anutin Charnvirakul, <b>Thailand’s</b> prime minister, declared victory in a <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2026/01/26/thailands-liberals-face-a-tricky-election" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">general election</a> for his conservative Bhumjaithai Party. With nearly all votes counted, Bhumjaithai looked set to win about 192 seats, with the reformist People’s Party taking 117. The result is a blow for the People’s Party, which, under a different name, was blocked by the army-appointed Senate from taking power in 2023, despite winning the election.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Iran’s</b> security forces reportedly arrested four people, including three senior reformist politicians, for attempting to “disrupt the country’s social and political order” and working “for the benefit” of Israel and America. Earlier an Iranian court sentenced <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2023/10/06/a-woman-described-as-irans-nelson-mandela-wins-the-nobel-peace-prize" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">Narges Mohammadi</a>, a human-rights advocate and Nobel peace prize laureate, to seven-and-a-half additional years in prison. She has spent more than a decade imprisoned for various anti-government offences.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Israel’s</b> cabinet approved measures to make it easier for <a href="https://www.economist.com/interactive/middle-east-and-africa/2025/09/03/rampant-and-relentless-israel-s-settlers-make-their-move" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">Jewish settlers</a> to buy and register land in the <b>West Bank</b>. The country’s hawkish defence and finance ministers, Israel Katz and Bezalel Smotrich, said that repealing Jordanian-era laws that ban land sales to Jews would remove “decades-old barriers” to development in the territory.  Palestine’s presidency said the new measures amount to “annexation and displacement”. It called them “illegal, null and void”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Morgan McSweeney</b> resigned as <b>Sir Keir Starmer’s</b> chief of staff. He had encouraged the prime minister to appoint Peter Mandelson as Britain’s ambassador to America despite Lord Mandelson’s links to Jeffrey Epstein, a dead sex offender. Mr McSweeney was an architect of Labour’s resounding electoral victory in 2024. His resignation is unlikely to quell <a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2026/02/06/who-might-succeed-sir-keir-starmer-as-britains-prime-minister" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_6">speculation</a> about a challenge to Sir Keir’s leadership.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The Seattle Seahawks beat the New England Patriots to win the<b> Super Bowl</b>, thanks to a dominant defensive display. <b>Bad Bunny</b>, a Puerto Rican singer, became the first Latin star singing primarily in Spanish to headline the <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2026/02/06/america-may-be-reaching-peak-spanish" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_7">half-time show</a>. The performance mostly steered clear of strong political statements, despite speculation he might take a swipe at Donald Trump.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260209-060018</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 06:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>