<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 10, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Sir Keir Starmer</b>, the most unpopular British prime minister since records began, looks to have held on to his job—<a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2026/02/09/why-sir-keir-starmer-remains-on-the-brink" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">for now</a>—after defending his record in front of disgruntled Labour MPs. Only one senior figure, Anas Sarwar, the Scottish Labour leader, urged him to resign for “mistakes” that include the <a href="https://www.economist.com/britain/2026/02/04/britains-worst-political-scandal-of-this-century" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_1">appointment of Peter Mandelson</a> as ambassador to America. Sir Keir vowed not to plunge Britain “into chaos” by quitting.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>American</b> forces struck a vessel suspected of carrying drugs in the Pacific Ocean, killing two people. At least 121 people have been killed in the Trump administration’s campaign against what it says are seafaring drug traffickers. Separately, American troops captured a tanker transporting <b>Venezuelan oil</b> in the Indian Ocean. The Department of War accused the vessel of breaching the country’s “quarantine” of crude exports from <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/01/27/how-to-tell-if-venezuela-is-heading-for-democracy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_2">Venezuela</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Air Canada cancelled all <b>flights</b> to <b>Cuba</b> after the Caribbean country said it would not be able to supply international airlines with aviation fuel. The Trump administration has enforced an oil blockade on the island, claiming its government is a <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/01/05/cubas-regime-is-now-in-donald-trumps-sights" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">threat to America</a>. On Monday Claudia Sheinbaum, Mexico’s president, accused America of trying to “strangle” Cuba and vowed to help through “diplomatic actions”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Alphabet </b>will reportedly raise $20bn from a bond sale on Monday, as it seeks to finance its investments in AI. Last week the tech giant said capital expenditure could hit $185bn this year, including a splurge on <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/09/30/the-murky-economics-of-the-data-centre-investment-boom" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">data centres</a>. In a rare move for a technology company, Alphabet is also reportedly hawking a 100-year bond to banks.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Israel </b>struck southern <b>Lebanon</b>, killing four people, including a child, local officials said. Israel said it was targeting members of <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/01/26/hizbullah-irans-most-powerful-proxy-has-been-humbled" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">Hizbullah</a>. The Shia militia called the attacks a “dangerous escalation”. Lebanese authorities say Israeli forces have killed about 400 people since the ceasefire that followed Israel’s war with Hizbullah in 2024.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>King Charles III </b>admitted “profound concern” over allegations involving his brother, Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, and <b>Jeffrey</b> <b>Epstein</b>. Police are assessing a complaint that the former Prince Andrew shared confidential government material with the deceased sex offender. Meanwhile Ghislaine Maxwell, <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/05/jeffrey-epsteins-ghost-is-haunting-the-grand-old-men-of-capitalism" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_6">Epstein’s</a> accomplice, who is serving a 20-year sentence, refused to answer questions from America’s House Oversight Committee, invoking her Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Organisers of the <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2025/12/18/italy-is-using-the-winter-olympics-to-appeal-to-the-ultra-wealthy" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_7">Milan-Cortina</a> <b>Winter Olympics</b> launched an investigation into why their medals keep breaking. Several athletes said that the ribbons on their medals had detached from the gongs. Breezy Johnson, an American skier, warned recipients not to “jump in them”, after hers came apart while jigging about in excitement at winning gold.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260210-060017</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 06:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>