<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 08:06:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 22, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><strong>Donald Trump </strong>announced he would raise his new global <strong>tariff </strong>to 15% with immediate effect. Mr Trump had initially set a 10% rate under Section 122—which allows the president to impose border levies for up to 150 days—after the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2026/02/20/the-supreme-court-strikes-down-donald-trumps-tariffs">struck down the bulk of his other tariffs</a>. Corporate America hopes to recoup an estimated $170bn in duties, a question the justices did not address.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Students at universities across <strong>Iran</strong> held anti-government protests to mark the start of a new semester. The rallies were the first since the regime brutally clamped down on similar demonstrations last month. The protests took place amid the prospect of <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/19/the-moment-of-reckoning-between-america-and-iran">imminent war</a> with America. Mr Trump has given Iran a maximum of 15 days to reach a deal over its nuclear programme.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Pakistan</strong> carried out several strikes along its border with <strong>Afghanistan</strong>. Attaullah Tarar, Pakistan’s information minister, said the “intelligence-based” operation targeted camps belonging to <a href="https://www.economist.com/asia/2025/10/16/border-clashes-erupt-between-pakistan-and-afghanistan-again">Tehreek-e-Taliban Pakistan</a>, a militant group believed to be responsible for a bombing in the capital, Islamabad, earlier this month. Mr Tarar said Pakistan had “conclusive evidence” that the TTP was acting at the “behest” of leaders based in Afghanistan.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Emmanuel Macron</strong>, France’s president, called for calm ahead of a <strong>far-right march</strong> in Lyon. The protest follows the death of Quentin Deranque, a nationalist activist who was kicked and beaten to death by masked men last Saturday. Eleven people, including two parliamentary aides to a hard-left MP, were detained over the incident. Seven are being investigated for murder. The killing has become a <a href="https://www.economist.com/briefing/2025/12/11/once-a-pariah-the-national-rally-is-now-frances-most-popular-party">liability for the left</a> ahead of local elections in March that are expected to shape next year’s presidential race.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Shares in <strong>cyber-security</strong> companies, such as CrowdStrike and Cloudflare, fell after <strong>Anthropic</strong> released a new feature in its Claude artificial-intelligence model. The <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/07/23/the-dark-horse-of-ai-labs">AI firm</a> said the tool “scans codebases for security vulnerabilities” and suggests fixes. The cyber-security slump is part of a broader sell-off in software-related shares, as investors worry about the impact of AI.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Boaz Weinstein</strong>, an activist investor, has offered to buy shares in <strong>Blue Owl’s</strong> business development companies at an expected discount of 20-35%. On Wednesday the private-credit firm spooked markets by permanently restricting exits from a debt fund targeted at retail investors. Mr Weinstein’s offer would allow investors to cash out, albeit while taking a significant loss.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Israeli </strong>strikes killed at least ten people in eastern <strong>Lebanon</strong>, according to local media. The Israeli army said it had hit sites belonging to Hizbullah, a <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/01/26/hizbullah-irans-most-powerful-proxy-has-been-humbled">Lebanese militia</a>, because they were “a violation of the understanding between Israel and Lebanon”. Earlier Israel struck a Palestinian refugee camp in southern Lebanon, alleging it was a Hamas “command centre”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Word of the week: </strong><i>Aso ebi,</i> a term for the matching fabrics guests wear to Nigerian weddings<i>, </i>meaning “cloth of the kin” in Yoruba. <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/19/the-global-triumph-of-nigerian-fashion">Read the full story.</a></p>
        <hr>
        <p>
      <i>Get a behind-the-scenes look at how we choose and design each week’s front cover by subscribing to the  Cover Story newsletter.</i>
    </p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Israel’s uncertain wait over Iran</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>The Israeli security cabinet will meet on Sunday, a week after it was originally meant to—a postponement that indicates Israel’s leaders are not yet fully sure if America, its main ally, <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/19/the-moment-of-reckoning-between-america-and-iran">will attack Iran</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Israel has long viewed Iran’s nuclear programme as an unacceptable threat and has been <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/01/11/israel-hopes-for-regime-change-in-iran">pushing America</a> to force Iran to put strict limits on its arsenal. Last week Donald Trump said “nothing definitive” was decided after a meeting with Binyamin Netanyahu, Israel’s prime minister, during which Iran was discussed.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Israel is preparing to join in if America does decide to attack, and readying itself for the consequences. The last time the pair struck, in June 2025, Iran retaliated by firing more than 500 missiles on Israeli cities. Most were intercepted, but enough got through to kill 28 people. Having spent years lobbying American presidents to take a harder line on Iran, Israel must now wait for Mr Trump to make up his mind.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Hungary’s unusually open election</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>The EU’s most consequential election campaign of the year began this weekend. Viktor Orban has been Hungary’s prime minister for almost 16 years. During this time, he has repeatedly refused to support Ukraine, and courted Vladimir Putin and Donald Trump. At home, meanwhile, Mr Orban has dismantled democratic institutions and rewritten chunks of Hungary’s constitution. The European Parliament admits his regime is in effect an “electoral autocracy”.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>But for the first time since 2010, Mr Orban has <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2026/01/29/peter-magyar-could-defeat-viktor-orban-hungarys-leader">a formidable opponent</a> in the election on April 12th. Peter Magyar was once prominent in Fidesz, Mr Orban’s populist-right party. He defected in 2024 and became leader of the centre-right Tisza, which is backed by young, educated, urban Hungarians. Tisza currently has a large lead in most polls. While Hungary’s gerrymandered electoral system still gives Fidesz a huge advantage—as do the handouts Mr Orban uses to tempt voters—there is a chance he might actually lose this race.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Donald Trump’s economic coercion of Cuba</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>The Trump administration is <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2026/02/12/cubas-fate-may-be-in-marco-rubios-hands">piling the pressure</a> on Cuba’s communist regime. The island has suffered for decades under government mismanagement combined with American sanctions. In January the White House threatened to impose tariffs on any country that supplies it with oil. Venezuela and Mexico have halted energy imports, resulting in more blackouts and grounded flights.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Marco Rubio, the secretary of state, has long wished to see his parents’ homeland freed from 67 years of Communist Party rule. The administration is pressing for a genuine opening of Cuba’s state-dominated economy. Mr Rubio is reportedly holding secret conversations with the grandson of Raúl Castro, the brother of former leader <a href="https://www.economist.com/briefing/2016/12/03/the-life-and-times-of-fidel-castro">Fidel</a>, according to <i>Axios</i>, a news site.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>For a one-party system entrenched since 1959, any regime change would be historic. Cuba’s leadership, more ideological and diffuse than Venezuela’s, knows how to play a long game. But the Trump administration is betting the economic collapse is so severe that this time that will not be possible.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Rocky relations between Japan and South Korea</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>Two islets in the Sea of Japan have long caused diplomatic spats. South Korea argues that Japan illegitimately annexed “Dokdo” in 1905. Meanwhile, Japan insists South Korea has illegally occupied “Takeshima” since the 1950s.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Japan’s annual “Takeshima Day”, which was instituted in 2005 and falls this Sunday, is meant to reinforce its claim. Since 2013 the government has sent only junior ministers to attend the ceremony in Shimane, the nearest prefecture. Last year Takaichi Sanae, the Japanese prime minister who recently <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2026/02/12/the-worlds-most-powerful-woman">won a landslide election victory</a>, declared that a cabinet minister should “proudly attend”. South Korea would inevitably interpret that as a provocation.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Instead, Ms Takaichi has sailed for calmer waters. In October she agreed to “develop bilateral relations” with Lee Jae-myung, the South Korean president. The pair, both drummers, played together in January. And Ms Takaichi has rowed back her position on Takeshima, too: the same lowly level of minister is being dispatched as last year.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>No BAFTAs, please, we’re British</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>The British Academy Film Awards are billed as the biggest night of the year for British cinema. But this Sunday’s ceremony won’t feature much of the country’s talent. The frontrunner for the best-film prize is Paul Thomas Anderson’s “One Battle After Another”, an American black comedy with 14 nominations. Its closest rival is “<a href="https://www.economist.com/culture/2025/05/02/the-morals-of-sinners-a-fantasia-of-vampires-and-the-blues">Sinners</a>”, a yarn about vampires in Mississippi made by Ryan Coogler, another American.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Timothée Chalamet, yet another American, is expected to win best actor for his turn in “Marty Supreme”, a table-tennis caper set in New York. Jessie Buckley will probably take home the best-actress trophy for playing Shakespeare’s wife in “Hamnet”. Though the film is technically British, it has an American-based, Chinese director (Chloé Zhao) and two Irish stars (Paul Mescal and Ms Buckley). Wunmi Mosaku, who is British-Nigerian, is nominated for her excellent supporting performance in “Sinners”. But the only Briton guaranteed a big moment is Alan Cumming, the evening’s host.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Mini crossword</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>We publish a new interactive edition of our crossword daily, allowing you to enter and check the answers and see explanations. Try it <a href="https://www.economist.com/interactive/mini-crossword">here</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>There are two sets of clues, one for seasoned cruciverbalists and the other for less experienced solvers. Both give the same answers.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>
      <strong>Cryptic clues</strong>
    </p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>1 across</i> - Sounds a bit eggy for such a heavy burden (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>2 across</i> - Very much in German taxi(4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>3 across </i>- America online went backwards, then north, for a borrowed sum (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>1 down - </i>You, SK looney, chaotically declared martial law (4,3,4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p>
      <strong>Straight clues</strong>
    </p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>1 across</i> - Wooden bar between two animals (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>2 across</i> - American ride-hailing app (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>3 across </i>- Something to pay back (4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p><i>1 down - </i>Former South Korean president banged up for life (4,3,4)</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Email all four answers, along with your home city and country, by 9am GMT on Monday to <a href="mailto:crossword@economist.com">crossword@economist.com</a>. We will pick three winners at random and crown them in Tuesday’s edition.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>The winners of the week’s quiz</h3>
        <hr>
        <p>Thank you to everyone who took part in this week’s quiz. The winners, chosen at random, were:</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Gavin Meacham</strong>, Canberra, Australia</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Kate Marshall</strong>, Toronto, Canada</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Vittorio Ferrario</strong>, Geneva, Switzerland</p>
        <hr>
        <p>They all gave the correct answers of: scarlet (the disease is scarlet fever), hounds, Ginger Baker, Hudson’s Bay company and Thomas Watson (“Mr Watson, come here, I want to see you,” Bell said). The theme is Sherlock Holmes who featured in the stories “A Study in Scarlet” and “The Hound of the Baskervilles”, and lived in Baker Street with a housekeeper Mrs Hudson and friend Dr Watson.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>The questions were:</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Monday: </strong>What colour, traditionally worn by a cardinal, is also associated with a childhood disease?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Tuesday: </strong>Grey, blood and basset are words that precede the name of what type of dog?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Wednesday:</strong> Which famous drummer was one of the founder members of the rock group Cream?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Thursday: </strong>Which Canadian business, originally founded in 1670 and noted for its department stores, was finally liquidated in 2025?</p>
        <hr>
        <p><strong>Friday: </strong>When Alexander Graham Bell made the first telephone call, who did he call?</p>
        <hr>
        <p>This is the world you have made yourself, now you have to live in it.</p>
        <hr>
        <h3>Nina Simone</h3>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260222-080640</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 08:06:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>