<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 20:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 11, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>America’s economy</b> added 130,000 jobs in January, almost double the number that analysts had been expecting, indicating that <a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2025/11/30/why-worries-about-american-job-losses-are-overstated" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">the labour market</a> might have picked up after months of apparent stagnation. The unemployment rate also fell to 4.3%, a slight dip from the previous month. The figures may put off the Federal Reserve from lowering interest rates as fast as Donald Trump would like.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>America’s aviation regulator closed and then quickly reopened the skies over <b>El Paso</b> airport in Texas. The FAA said the ban was for “special security reasons”; the Trump administration claimed that <b>drones</b> belonging to <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2025/11/10/making-mexico-less-of-a-gangsters-paradise" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">Mexican drug cartels</a> had entered American airspace. But surprised local officials and a Democratic congresswoman for El Paso questioned this explanation. Other sources reportedly said the closure was for a test of anti-drone technology.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>A shooter killed at least nine people at a school and nearby residence in the Canadian province of <b>British Columbia</b>, before reportedly turning the weapon on themself. Authorities said that at least 25 other people were injured during the attack in Tumbler Ridge. Police described the attacker as female. Further information, including a motive, has yet to be confirmed.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>In a speech to mark the 47th anniversary of the Islamic revolution, <b>Iran’s</b> president said the country is ready to have its <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/04/donald-trump-wants-to-end-americas-half-century-conflict-with-iran" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_4">nuclear programme</a> inspected, and reiterated that it was not building an atomic weapon. His address came ahead of a meeting between Binyamin Netanyahu, Israel’s prime minister, and <b>Donald Trump</b>. The two leaders will discuss possible military action against Iran.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Heineken </b>said it would cut up to 6,000 jobs—roughly 7% of its global workforce—to reduce costs as demand for beer continues to go flat in Europe and America. The Dutch brewer saw a 1.2% drop in beer sales in 2025 compared with the year before. Its share price rose by 4% in early trading on the announcement.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Mistral AI</b> pledged to spend €1.2bn ($1.4bn) building data centres in Sweden in partnership with EcoDataCentre, a Swedish data-centre operator. <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/03/06/mistral-europes-biggest-ai-startup-is-blowing-hot" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_6">The French startup</a> says it wants to boost AI capabilities in Europe and reduce the continent’s dependence on American technology. Valued at almost €12bn, the firm remains considerably smaller than its American and Chinese rivals.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Switzerland </b>will hold a referendum in June on capping its 9.1m population at 10m. The proposal, which is supported by the right-wing Swiss People’s Party, gained the 100,000 signatures required to put it to a national vote. Proponents of the measure want to limit the number of immigrants and asylum-seekers; the population has grown faster in recent years than in most neighbouring countries.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260211-200015</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 20:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>