<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 12:53:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 04, 2026</title>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p><b>Novo Nordisk’s </b>shares plunged almost 20% after it warned that sales and profits would fall this year. The Danish maker of <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-world-ahead/2025/11/10/a-second-helping-of-weight-loss-drugs-is-coming" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_1:gobbet_1">weight-loss drugs</a> said intensifying competition and policymakers’ efforts to cut prices for treatments in America were ending years of rapid growth, shocking investors who had expected only a modest slowdown. Novo reported sales of DKr309bn ($49bn) last year, up 10% at constant exchange rates.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>America’s navy</b> shot down an <b>Iranian drone</b> that it said “aggressively approached” the <i>USS Abraham Lincoln</i>, an aircraft-carrier in the Arabian Sea, with “unclear intent”. Last week Donald Trump <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/01/28/is-america-about-to-attack-iran" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_2:gobbet_2">sent an armada</a> to the Middle East, and has repeatedly threatened to <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2026/02/01/the-violence-in-iran-could-lead-to-civil-war" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_3:gobbet_2">strike Iran</a> if it does not agree to new limits on its nuclear programme and cutting ties with regional proxy groups.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>At least 18 people, including four children, were killed in <b>Israeli </b>strikes across <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2025/12/18/two-months-in-the-gaza-ceasefire-is-floundering" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_4:gobbet_3">Gaza</a>, Palestinian officials said. Israel also halted the evacuation of patients through the <b>Rafah</b> crossing with Egypt just two days after it reopened. The Israel Defence Forces said it launched the strikes after a gunman shot and seriously wounded a reservist.</p>
        <hr>
        <p>Mr Trump signed a bill to end the partial government shutdown, after it narrowly passed the <b>House of Representatives</b> by 217-214 votes. The measure will fund several agencies until September and the Department of Homeland Security until February 13th, allowing lawmakers to continue negotiating restrictions on <a href="https://www.economist.com/briefing/2026/01/28/immigration-agents-have-become-donald-trumps-personal-posse" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_5:gobbet_4">immigration-enforcement agents</a>.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Seif al-Islam Qaddafi</b>, the son of <b>Libya’s</b> former dictator Muammar, was reportedly killed. The circumstances are unclear, but his lawyer said he was assassinated at home by “unknown assailants”. Mr Qaddafi <i>fils</i> was once seen as the most influential person in <a href="https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2021/10/02/could-libya-be-ruled-again-by-a-qaddafi" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_6:gobbet_5">Libya</a> after his father, and his heir apparent, before the regime collapsed. He ran for president in 2021 but the elections were derailed.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Tech stocks</b> fell in Asia after a similar sell-off in America. It began after <b>Anthropic</b>, a privately-held artificial-intelligence firm, launched an AI tool that can automate some legal work. Legal- and data-services companies suffered first: shares in Thomson Reuters, for example, sank by nearly 16%. The sell-off then spread across the wider <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2026/02/01/why-software-stocks-are-getting-pummelled" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_7:gobbet_6">software sector</a>. The tech-heavy NASDAQ index closed down by 1.4%.</p>
        <hr>
        <p><b>Walmart’s</b> market value rose above $1trn for the first time. Investors have been impressed by the <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/05/15/how-walmart-became-a-tech-giant-and-took-over-the-world" data-analytics="espresso_gobbets:link_8:gobbet_7">retail giant’s efforts</a> to develop new technology to take on e-commerce firms such as Amazon. Walmart recently signed deals with Alphabet and OpenAI that allow its customers to use AI to buy goods.</p>
      ]]></description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260204-125311</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 12:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>