<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>The Economist - World in Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.economist.com/the-world-in-brief</link>
    <description>Catch up quickly on the global stories that matter</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 21:54:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>World in Brief - February 03, 2026</title>
      <description>America’s navy shot down an Iranian drone that it said “aggressively approached” the USS Abraham Lincoln, an aircraft-carrier in the Arabian Sea, with “unclear intent”. Last week Donald Trump sent an armada to the Middle East, and has repeatedly threatened to strike Iran if it does not agree to new limits on its nuclear programme and to cut ties with regional proxy groups.<br/><br/>America’s House of Representatives narrowly passed a bill by 217-214 votes that would end the partial government shutdown. Mr Trump is expected to promptly sign it into law. The measure will fund several agencies until September and the Department of Homeland Security until February 13th, allowing lawmakers to continue negotiating restrictions on immigration-enforcement agents.<br/><br/>Disney said that Josh D’Amaro will become its chief executive on March 18th. Mr D’Amaro, who currently runs the company’s theme parks, will replace Bob Iger, who has been in his second stint in the top job since 2022. Investors worry about the century-old studio’s ability to innovate as technology companies reshape the entertainment industry.<br/><br/>Walmart’s market value rose above $1trn for the first time. Investors have been impressed by the retail giant’s efforts to develop new technology to take on e-commerce firms such as Amazon. The company recently signed deals with Alphabet and Openai to allow users to buy goods from Walmart using their ai products such as Gemini and Chatgpt.<br/><br/>Russia struck Ukraine’s energy infrastructure, ending a pause on such attacks requested by Mr Trump because of freezing temperatures. Ukrainian authorities said the strikes hit power facilities in the capital, Kyiv, as well as several other regions. The bombardment came as American, Russian and Ukrainian officials prepare to meet for talks this week in Abu Dhabi.<br/><br/>Spain’s prime minister, Pedro Sánchez, said his government would seek to ban social media for under-16s. He called social networks a “failed state in which laws are ignored” and pledged to force platforms to introduce “effective age-verification systems”. Governments in Europe and Asia are considering introducing such measures after Australia did so in December.<br/><br/>nasa’s bid to return humans to the Moon hit a snag. America’s space agency aborted a “wet dress rehearsal” of its Artemis II mission, a test of the launch system’s fuelling equipment, because of a liquid-hydrogen leak. nasa said the problem would delay the launch of Artemis II, which aims to send four astronauts around the Moon, until at least March.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">economist-wib-20260203</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 21:54:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>